Now we're going to talk about physical digital
devices. So it there are no real digital devices.
Everything in this world is analog. So we sort of
layer an abstraction on top of an analog world.
And so think of digital as analog systems
that are built to have two relatively stable
states and they require some kind of an input to
change the state. But once the state is changed,
it's stable again. Okay? So it there's a state
state transition. So if we look at a pen,
by the way, capturing the new state, the technical
term for that is called latching. You know,
you here comes a change state, you you like latch
it, you grab it, and you keep it. And then the
stable time is when you've kept the state. So you
often find at least in physical digital devices
that there is a clicking associated with it.
So here's a pen, a retractable pen. All right,
there you go. Retractable pen. Click, click,
click, click. Okay, now so we'll decide that
zero is when it's retracted and one is when it's
not. And so it's stable. I don't have to touch
it to keep the one. And when it's zero, I don't
have to touch it to keep the zero. But it's also
you have to put input to switch it from zero
to one. But if you don't push it far enough,
it goes back to zero. So zero is stable and slight
variations of input does not disturb the zero. It
comes back to zero. But if you put enough input,
hear the click, then it's a one, right? And so
there is a two states and a transition period. And
that transition period is when there is some input
required to change the state. And so that is the
notion of digital. We we call one of the states
one and one of the states zero. So a classic use
of this for hundreds of years is clocks. So clocks
are sort of a digital where the pendulum would
go back and forth, tick tock, tick tock, and then
inside of it, a little gear would move for each
second. And then that would count up the seconds
to make a minute and then count up the minutes
to make an hour with a series of gears. Very much
like the anti mechanism. And what's even cooler
for a cuckoo clock is that at particular moments
in time, it runs a little mechanical program to
make a little birdie come out and tweet. So cuckoo
clocks are an early form of of programming
that's all hardware and all analog, but it's
analog digital because of the tick- tock and the
counters that count the ticks and the ts. [Music]
So, another device that is a counter that carries
and frankly this device could be the inside of a
cuckoo clock. It's just a little easier for us to
understand it. So, what these are, let me show you
close up here. So, these are little devices that
are used for shopping and they have dollars. Let
me get my pen here. They have dollars, dimes,
and cents. And if you're going to buy something
for 15 cents, you can put the five in for five
cents and then one in and you and then I buy
something for 25 cents, put two dimes and five
five cents and it's carrying all along. Okay. Now,
how does this work? It is a physical digital
device. You can see that it's clicking. So,
let's take a look inside the device. So, here's
the inside of the device, and you can see right
away that there is some springs in here. Each one
has a spring, and there's a specific shape of the
of the thing we're pushing down. And there's some
flexibility in it. So, all of this is to get to
the point where we can press an input and that
input changes it, right? So, if I press it down,
it doesn't quite change. That's the old stable
part. But if I press it far enough, it clicks and
then it changes. Now, we're about to see, we're on
nine right now, and we're going to click one more
time, and we're going to see the carry. This is
a ripple carry. We're going to learn about later
in half adders and full adders, we're going to
learn about ripple carry. But you can watch as
the ripple carry happens, this little white thing
here is going to go up and push. It's going to
act as if it pushed the middle one. It's going to
move it, but instead pushing the sense is going to
Oops, I pushed the wrong one. Pushing the sense
is going to move that. So, if I go around and
do 10 more of these, you'll see it'll come down.
It's seven and now it's clicked to eight. So, that
that's how we carry when we get beyond 10. And so,
this notion of ripple carry and multiple values,
we're going to build this into actually electronic
hardware uh coming up. So once you can build an
adding machine with some kind of iteration, you
can turn addition into multiplication. And that's
because multiplication is merely repeated
addition. Now I don't have a multiplier,
but I do have a an an adder that's a little
tougher. This is metal. It's many things. It
can do addition. It can do subtraction. And then
eventually you would put something like this with
a motor on it or a crank on it. And then you could
build a physical mechanical multiplier. Addition
and subtraction and multiplication are not the
only things that we needed to do. We need to do
things like logarithms, sign and cosine. And today
we would just use a hand calculator and we put in
whatever and we click the sign button and out it
comes. Now that to someone in the 1930s would be a
miracle that you can ask for the sign or cosine or
logarithm of any number and it just comes out on
a little screen. This is more powerful than any
computer in 1930. So what they had to do though
those functions are still there s and cosine and
logarithms have to do with things like curves and
the motion of spacecraft etc. And so we needed
to know all this stuff. So there's a couple ways
to do it. Now, one of the things we talked about
already with logarithms was the fact that we have
a slide rule. And the slide rule's a slide rule
upside no slide rule is not upside down. The slide
rule that basically just converts linear numbers
to logarithmic numbers and then it uses sliding
and addition adding by moving along this line that
equates to multiplication. So logarithms we we in
the in the 30s, 40s and 50s, we use slide rules
with carefully crafted scales and movement to turn
the more complex multiplication into addition.
But for things like s and cosine and just
looking up logarithms a little more precisely,
we basically created this book. We had this book,
standard mathematical tables. And this was a
thing you every engineer would buy. And if you
wanted to look logarithms up, this is the a book
of four place decimal common logarithms. And you
would look things up and you would find four or
five digits of precision. And if you keep going,
you got logarithms of trigonometric functions,
squares, s and cosine in their product,
hyperbolic functions. Okay, we don't even want to
know that stuff. Integrals. Okay, so this was the
way you did complex calculations before we had
hand calculators. This is all replaced for all
intents and purposes by modern hand calculators,
but the transistor hasn't been invented yet. Now,
there were devices that were designed in a sense
to create that book. The Babbage difference engine
was something that was imagined in the 1820s that
was had gears and little cogs, little carry adders
just like the stuff we just saw that could compute
up to seventh order polomials like x to the 7th,
x to the 6, x 5th. And the reason that was
so important is you can approximate a lot of
functions using polomials with various constants
on those polomials. So if you could put a seventh
order polinomial into this machine and then
run it for a while, you could generate a table
of sign or different polomial would generate a
table cosine or logarithms. And the cool thing
about this is this was designed to actually
have a printer which would do the computation
and then print the result out so that you could
make a book out of this thing. And and Charles
Babage designed it all in the 1800s and he built
a tiny prototype. But it turns out that, you know,
ran out of money, ran out of time. A full-scale
system based on his designs was built in 1991,
and it worked exactly as Babage expected it. It
was intended to be powered by a steam engine,
although if you ever see one running,
usually it's a human that's cranking it.
Now another way that we built the content of
these tables in these books is using computers.
Except in the early days computer was a word for
a job description for a human being. So the idea
of a computer is they would have some kind of
a calculator probably could do addition and
multiplication and this person would carefully put
numbers in run the calculator and compute using
some of those polinomial things often sign and log
and then record the results and these these rooms
full of people would do these calculations over
and over and over for different input values and
get the output values for various functions and
then write them down and that's what built human
computers built many of the early data in these
early books. Now computers when computers started
electronic computers started to happen it was
natural to think of the task that these electronic
computers were doing as very similar to the task
the repetitive tasks that the human computers were
doing. And so that's how things we call computers
today were named computers. They're named after
people. And the movie, one of my favorite movies,
Hidden Figures, explores the shift from sort of
human to electronic computers where they were
a bunch of people and they were doing human
computer work. Um, and then they moved into uh the
electronic computer work and using uh Forran etc.
[Music] [Applause] [Music]